in our previous solution
the prompt we display to our user
suggests that we are expecting them to
input either y or n however we don't
actually ensure that the user inputs
either y
or n we only verify whether or not the
user input is equal to y
now we want to actually require the user
to input either y
or n and if they don't we'll issue an
error message to the user and prompt
them again
let's put our existing code into a loop
[Music]
now we don't want to run our code yet
because right now we have an
infinite loop so we want to think about
when we want to break out of this loop
from the problem description we know
that we want to continue prompting the
user for their input
if their input is not y or n
and we're going to represent that with
our loop
so let's think about the condition in
which we would want to break out of our
loop
we can create an array of what we would
consider acceptable characters
[Music]
so in this case we'll use y and n and
then we can call the array include
method
on this array of characters and this
method returns a boolean
based on whether or not the calling
array includes
the argument so we'll pass our choice
local variable
which holds a reference to the user
input to the include method
and ruby will check whether or not the
calling array includes our argument
if it does we'll break out of our loop
so for now i'm going to comment out the
rest of this code and let's just see how
our break condition is working
[Music]
if i input something other than y or n
you can see that our loop continues to
run we're prompted again
however if i input a y
we've broken out of our loop and our
program has completed
execution
now we know that we want to display an
error message to the user
if their input is anything other than y
or n
and we want to place the output of this
error message
after the break condition in other words
if we don't break out of our loop then
we want to display the error message to
the user
because that means their input was not
valid
let's run the program again
this time when we input something other
than y or
n we'll expect to see an error message
and you can see the error message is
displayed and we've been prompted again
so that's exactly what we want to see at
this point
if i input n
we've broken out of the loop
[Music]
so now we need to think about where we
want to put this
if statement that will print something
if our user input was
y
[Music]
if we leave this if statement where it
is currently
line 9 will never be executed
and that's because on line 5 we break
out of our loop
if the user input was y or n so there
will never be a situation where we reach
line 8 still within our loop and choice
is equal to y
so the solution here is to move this if
statement outside of our loop
[Music]
if choice is equal to y or n we'll break
out of our loop
and then we can check whether choice is
equal to y and print
something if it is
so let's run the code now and see if
we're getting the expected behavior
[Music]
first i'll input something other than y
or n like a
g and i've received the message that the
input was invalid
and i'm prompted again this time i'll
input y
and you can see that an exception has
been raised ruby has identified
an undefined local variable or method
choice
on line 9.
[Music]
let's look at our code
the problem is choice on line nine
we initialize the local variable choice
within the block
passed to our loop this block creates an
inner
scope and because choice was initialized
in an inner scope
ruby cannot see it from this outer scope
here on line 9.
a simple way to solve this problem is to
initialize
choice in the outer scope
and initially just set it to nil and
then we'll reassign it within the loop
now let's run our code again and see if
it's working
we'll enter y again this is where we
received the exception last time
[Music]
and you can see that our code is running
appropriately
[Music]
let's input an n and make sure it runs
appropriately with an input of n
as well
[Music]
and it does
currently we've completed a good chunk
of the problem but there is one
remaining
issue if we run our program
and we input an uppercase y
you can see that our program thinks this
is invalid input
[Music]
and we'll see the same behavior if we
input in uppercase
n our program only responds to
lowercase characters y and n
[Music]
and typically when you're asking for
user input like this
you would want it to be case insensitive
so we want to recognize a y
whether it's uppercase or lowercase
calling the string down case method on
the user input when we store it in the
local variable
choice will cause all user input to be
in lowercase characters this makes it a
little bit easier for us to work with
[Music]
now if i run the program and input in
uppercase y
we're still going to see the same
behavior so
now our program is case insensitive
[Music]
now just to note there are a few ways
that you could
write this logic on line seven
there is a shortcut syntax in ruby to
write an array of strings
and i'll demonstrate that here on line 7
this syntax will be identified by ruby
as an array of strings
if you didn't happen to know the include
method
you could also write out your own logic
if choice is equal to y or choice is
equal
to n and this would work as well
[Music]
remember this simple loop structure when
you need to do some input validation in
your small programs
you